Roger Garis Papers
Roger Garis Papers
1855-1965
Garis, Roger, 1901-1967.
8 linear ft.
Papers of the American author and journalist. Correspondence (1932-1965) with family, authors, editors, publishers, lawyers, and literary agents; Garis family photographs and memorabilia; typescript articles, autobiograpy, essays, fiction, and plays. Correspondents include Brooks Atkinson, Josephine Lawrence, Arthur Mizener, José Quintero, Christiane Renauld, and Edward Barry Roberts.
148998
Biographical History
Roger Carroll Garis (1901-1967) was an American author and journalist. Over his career he wrote books for both children and adults as well as plays, short stories, and newspaper articles. His father, Howard R. Garis, was the author of the Uncle Wiggily stories and his mother, Lilian C. McNamara Garis, wrote books for girls.
Born September 10, 1901 in Newark, New Jersey, Roger Garis was educated at St. Benedict's Preparatory School in Newark, New Jersey, attended Princeton and Columbia Universities and graduated from New Jersey Law School with an LLB degree.
After serving a law clerkship, 1924-1925, Mr. Garis began his writing career by working for the Edward L. Stratemeyer syndicate specializing in books for boys, and soon began freelance writing of short stories for such magazines as Colliers, Redbook, Cosmopolitan, The American Magazine, The Saturday Evening Post and Liberty. He was a member of the staff of the Newark, New Jersey, Evening News from 1930-1935 and a special writer for the Waterbury, Connecticut, Republican. For the latter paper, he covered the Waterbury Conspiracy Trial which won the paper the Pulitzer Prize of 1939. He also served on the staff of the New York Times Magazine and was the author of plays and television dramas. During World War II, he was head head publications editor for the Office of War Information.
Mr. Garis was the author of Never Take Candy From a Stranger (1960) and My Father Was Uncle Wiggily (1966). His play The Pony Cart was produced in London and New York (1954-1960).
Mr. Garis's 1937 marriage to Adine Haviland was dissolved and in 1941, he married Mabel Robinson Burns. Of this marriage, there were three children: Leslie Ann, Roger Brooks, and Howard John. Mr. Garis and his family resided at Amherst, Massachusetts, at the time of his death on October 3, 1967.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Roger Garis Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence, 1932-1965, is with magazine editors, publishers, literary agents, motion picture producers, lawyers, friends and relatives. It is concerned with the writing and publishing of Mr. Garis's manuscripts, the production of his plays, and financial, legal and personal matters. Included are carbon copies of Office of War Information memoranda, 1942-1944. Literary agents with whom there is significant correspondence include Annie Laurie Williams, Inc. (1951-1957), Curtis Brown, Ltd. (1936-1959), Leland Hayward, Inc. (1936), MCA (Management Corporation of America) Artists, Ltd. (1956-1957), Peter Witt Associates (1957-1958), Rogers Terrill (1953-1963), and William Morris Agency (1948-1958). Significant individual correspondents include Brooks Atkinson (1954), Winthrop S. Dakin (1948-1964), Glen Farmer (1957-1960), Harold Freedman (1957-1960), Howard Garis (1949), Mabel Garis (1932-1951), Josephine Lawrence (1936-1937), Arthur M. Mizener (1951), Jose Quintero (1957), Christiane Renault (1932), and Edward Barry Roberts (1951-1957).
Memorabilia, 1920-1965, consists of biographical material, financial papers, material relating to family members and friends including genealogy, miscellaneous Office of War Information material, and photographs. Financial papers include bank books, promissory notes, contracts, leases, earnings reports, receipts, and wills and codicils.
Writings, 1934-1965, include articles, biography, fiction, letters to the editor, a magazine, The Pioneer (1949), published by Mr. Garis, notes, plays, poems, radio programs, a screen play, a television series, and writings for the Office of War Information. Also included here are a few manuscripts by other authors.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically except for family (Howard J. Garis, Mabel Garis and Leslie Garis), which are filed at the end of correspondence. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by subject. Writings are subdivided into those by Garis and those by others. Writings by Garis are arranged alphabetically by type; within each group, works are arranged alphabetically by title. Writings by others are alphabetical by author's name.
Related Material
has the papers of more than thirty children's literature authors; please refer to for complete listing. There is also related material in both the Rare Books and the general collections; please refer to for more information.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Dance and theatre; Radio, television, film; Atkinson, Brooks, 1894-1984.; Garis, Roger, 1901-1967 -- Archives.; Lawrence, Josephine, 1897?-1978.; Mizener, Arthur.; Quintero, José.; Renauld, Christiane.; Roberts, Edward Barry.; Garis family.; Authors, American.; Dramatists, American.; Autobiographies (literary works); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Authors.; Dramatists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Roger Garis, November 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1957, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1958-1965, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Garis, Howard J., 1961 (Box 2)
  - Garis, Leslie, 1956-1962 (Box 2)
  - Garis, Mabel, 1954-1964 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical material (Box 2)
  - Delehanty, Elizabeth (Box 2)
  - Financial papers
    - Bank books and promissory notes, 1942-1960 (Box 3)
    - Contracts, leases, mortgages, insurance policies, 1941-1961 (Box 3)
    - Earnings, 1941-1959 (Box 3)
    - Hospital and medical receipts, 1952-1962 (Box 3)
    - Income tax figures and returns, 1948-1961 (Box 3)
    - Scholarship statements for Leslie Garis, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - Wills and codicils, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Garis, Brooks, 1951-1962; school reports (Box 4)
  - Garis, Howard, 1960; school reports (Box 4)
  - Garis, Leslie, 1943-1960; school reports and miscellaneous, includes The Little Folks Animal Story Book inscribed "Grannie and Grandpa Garis 1948" (Box 4)
  - Garis, Mabel, 1942-1963; miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Genealogy, 1855-1900; includes New York State Volunteers Commission, naturalization papers and muster roll (Box 4)
  - High school yearbook, The Maroon Telelog, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Mexican trip, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Names and addresses (Box 4)
  - Office of War Information
    - Miscellaneous personal material, 1942-1944 (Box 4)
    - Publications, Chronology of Adolf Hitler's Life by Adolf Lande, Jul 1944; reproduction (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous publications (Box 5)
  - Pape, William J., publisher, Waterbury Republican, Jun 12, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Passports, social security card, 1927-1932 (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Actresses, "The Pony Cart", 1954 (Box 5)
    - Dog Races (Box 5)
    - Family (Box 5)
    - Howard Garis (Box 5)
    - Roger Garis (Box 5)
    - Houses (Box 5)
    - "Never Take Sweets From a Stranger" motion picture still (Box 5)
  - Programs
    - Roger Garis performance in The Trial, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Concert, theater, 1927; 1951 (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Lists of writings (Box 6)
  - Articles
    - "A Drop-Out Returns", 1964-1965; draft A, original typescript with revisions; draft B, typescript copy; draft C, typescript copy; in Good Housekeeping; reader's comments in Good Housekeeping (Box 6)
    - "The Pilot Who Came Back", typescript (Box 6)
    - "They Fly on Wings of Wind," New York Times, Sep 12, 1948 (Box 6)
    - "What a System," Liberty, Sep 28, 1946 (Box 6)
    - Untitled miscellaneous newspaper articles, 1939 (Box 6)
  - Autobiographical
    - Holograph notes, drafts A and B (Box 6)
  - Biography
    - "The Gift,", Draft A, typescript with revisions; draft B, typescript copy (Box 6)
    - My Father Was Uncle Wiggily
      - Drafts, drafts A through F, typescripts, typescript copies; some with revisions, some incomplete; 6 folders (Box 6)
      - Drafts, draft G, typescript copy with revisions, incomplete (Box 7)
      - Isolated pages, 1962; typescript and typescript copy with revisions (Box 7)
      - Discards, typescript with revisions (Box 7)
  - Essays and poems
    - Notebook (Box 7)
  - Fiction
    - Amusement Park, book reviews, 1934 (Box 7)
    - And Marry a Nice Girl, typescript and typescript copy (Box 7)
    - Birds of a Feather, novel, American, Feb 1945 (Box 7)
    - Busman's Holiday, Colliers, Jun 2, 1945 (Box 7)
    - The Chessboard, typescript copy (Box 7)
    - Fixed Star, serial in Country Gentlemen, Nov, Dec 1944, Jan, Feb 1945; notes, typescript and holograph (Box 7)
    - The Game, outline only, typescript (Box 7)
    - Get Your Girl, Liberty, Nov 14, 1942 (Box 7)
    - Good-by Broadway, Liberty, May 28, 1938 (Box 7)
    - Gorillas Aren't People, Liberty, Feb 25, 1939 (Box 7)
    - Hard River to Hold, typescript (Box 7)
    - Kid Brother, Cosmopolitan, Feb 1943 (Box 7)
    - The Lady Dreams of Tigers, typescript copy (Box 7)
    - Lead Story, Liberty, Oct 3, 1942 (Box 7)
    - The Lifeguard, typescript (Box 7)
    - Little Refugee, Colliers, Oct 26, 1940 (Box 7)
    - Love and Paula, draft A, typescript copy; draft B, typescript (Box 7)
    - Love Is Not Lost, Liberty, Nov 6, 1967 (Box 7)
    - The Lure, drafts A and B, typescript copies; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Never Been Kissed, typescript with revisions (Box 8)
    - Night Club Miracle, Liberty, Mar 23, 1940 (Box 8)
    - No Rules For Women, Liberty, May 22, 1937 (Box 8)
    - Nobody Else-Ever!, Redbook, Mar 1948 (Box 8)
    - Pale Hands I Loved, typescript (Box 8)
    - The Passionate Megacycle, draft A, typescript, pp. 1-303; draft B, typescript, Chapters XXIII-XXIX; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Petticoats Pick the Ponies, draft A, typescript copy with revisions; draft B, typescript copy (Box 8)
    - The Pony Cart, draft A, typescript copy with revisions, incomplete; draft B, typescript copy, pp. 1-309; chapter 1, holograph and typescript, 2 versions; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Raid in Wyoming, typescript copy (Box 9)
    - Remember Again, Liberty, Jan 11, 1941 (Box 9)
    - The Romance Attack, Liberty, Jul 24, 1943 (Box 9)
    - Saturday Night, typescript copy (Box 9)
    - Scarlet Runner, with Howard Garis, Colliers, Feb 10, 1951 (Box 9)
    - Straight, Place and Show, American Magazine, Nov 1947 (Box 9)
    - Strange Glory, Liberty, Aug 3, 1935 (Box 9)
    - The Stuck Pot, reproduction (Box 9)
    - Take Care of Me, Aug 6, 1962; drafts A, typescript with revisions; draft B, typescript; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - They Quarter the Heavens (alternate titles, University and Background)
      - Research material and holograph notes (Box 9)
      - Drafts, 1960; undated; draft A, holograph; draft B, typescript copy pp. 1-339; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Drafts, 1962-1963; 1965,; undated; drafts C-H; mix of holograph, typescripts, typescript copies, some with revisions; 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Triangle in the Sky, Liberty, Feb 27, 1937 (Box 10)
    - A Woman's Riddle at the Sphinx, Liberty, Dec 12, 1936 (Box 10)
    - Women and Houses Have Secrets, Redbook, Mar 1947 (Box 10)
    - A Young Man's Game, Liberty, Jan 14, 1939 (Box 10)
    - Unidentified notebook, plot only, holograph (Box 10)
  - Letters to the Editor
    - 1934-1960 (Box 10)
  - Magazine
    - Pioneer, Roger Garis, publisher, Mar 4, 18, and 25, Apr 15, 1949; incl. profit and loss statements (Box 10)
  - Notes
    - Miscellaneous, holograph and typescript (Box 10)
  - Plays
    - Amusement Park, 1957; 1959,; 1960,; undated; versions A-J; typescripts, typescript copies, one with revisions; 10 folders (Box 11)
    - The Anchorage, with Jonathan Eldridge, Television's Armstrong Circle Theater, Feb 1953; draft A, mimeo; draft B, rehearsal script, mimeo.; craft C, rev, and cut, mimeo; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - The Apartment, television play, undated; draft A, typescript; draft B, typescript copy; correspondence (Box 11)
    - The Bitter Wind, television play, drafts A and B; typescript copies; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - The Blue Balloon, drafts A-C, typescript copies; 3 folders (Box 12)
    - The China Shop, typescript copy (Box 12)
    - The Corporal's Christmas, television play, 1952; draft A, typescript with revisions; draft B, typescript copy; draft C, reproduction of typescript (Box 12)
    - Field of Battle, television play, typescript copy (Box 12)
    - Flame Out, television play, 1951; reproduction (Box 12)
    - Fog Station, television play, typescript and reproduction (Box 12)
    - A Hard River to Hold, outline, typescript (Box 12)
    - The High Places, television play, 1956; draft A, typescript with revisions; draft B, typescript copy; draft C, typescript copy (Box 12)
    - The Inn, television play, 1952; 1960; typescript copy; published, in Television Writing and Selling by Edward Barry Roberts (Box 13)
    - The Key, television play, 1952; typescript copy (Box 13)
    - Lone Crusader
      - Research material and notes, 1963; 1964; including copy of Lonely Crusader by Cecil Woodman Smith (Box 13)
      - Drafts, draft A, typescript copy with revisions; draft B, typescript; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - The Mayor, typescript (Box 13)
    - Moment of Memory, drafts A and B, typescript copies; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - One Hundred Red Convertibles, television play
      - Drafts, draft A, typescript copy with revisions (Box 13)
      - Drafts, draft B and C, typescript copies; draft D, reproduction; 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Paula, typescript copy (Box 14)
    - The Pony Cart
      - Drafts, draft A, typescript copy; draft B, reproduction; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Press notices and programs, 1954-1960 (Box 14)
    - The Prophet, typescript (Box 14)
    - The Renegade, holograph (Box 14)
    - The Sergeant, by Rod Serling, adapted for television by Roger Garis, 1952; reproduction (Box 14)
    - Some Don't
      - Drafts, draft A, typescript; draft B, typescript copy with revisions; draft C, typescript copy, Act 3 only; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Press notices and programs, 1963 (Box 14)
    - Sound of Running
      - Drafts, drafts A and B, typescript copies (Box 14)
      - Drafts, draft C, typescript (Box 15)
    - The Stuck Pot
      - Drafts, drafts A-D, typescripts copies with revisions; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Printed material, 1963 (Box 15)
    - Success Story (Box 15)
    - Swing High, Sweet Chariot, typescript copy (Box 15)
    - Way of Courage, Mar 13, 1952; draft A, typescript copy; draft B, typescript; draft C, reproduction; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Your Land and My Land
      - Drafts, draft A and B, typescript copies (Box 15)
      - Isolated pages, typescript (Box 16)
    - Unidentified fragments (Box 16)
  - Poems
    - Miscellaneous, typescript (Box 16)
  - Radio programs
    - U.S. Mutual Security Program (Box 16)
  - Screen plays
    - "Never Take Sweets From a Stranger" by John Hunter, adapted from "The Pony Cart" by Roger Garis, 1960-1961; reproduction, press notices and advertisements; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Television series
    - "Wing Commander" written with Barbara Merrill (proposed), 1963; synopsis only, typescript; correspondence (Box 16)
  - For Office of War Information
    - Miscellaneous, 1942-1943; reports, typescript; notes, holograph; press releases, printed material (Box 16)
  - By others
    - Brown, Woodbridge / "The Father's Testimony", typescript copy (Box 16)
    - Carter, Catherine/ "Near Eastern Night Club", typescript copy (Box 16)
    - Garis, Cleo / "Clancy", 1952; typescript (Box 16)
    - Garis, Leslie / "The First Christmas", typescript (Box 16)
    - Kimball, James / "No Harbor", typescript (Box 16)
    - Lee, Ellen / "Get Up Sometime," "Supreme Court" and "Birth is a Painful Thing" (Box 16)
    - Renault, Christiane, typescript (Box 16)